The Love Story of a Bold Buccaneer
The Black Pirate is a adventure, drama, action film directed by Albert Parker.
A nobleman vows to avenge the death of his father by the hands of pirates.
To this end, he infiltrates the pirate band; Acting in character, he single-handedly captures a merchant vessel, but
things are complicated when he finds that there is a beautiful young woman of royal blood aboard.
The Duke of Arnoldo / The Black Pirate, played by Douglas Fairbanks.
Princess Isobel, played by Billie Dove.
Pirate Captain, played by Anders Randolf.
MacTavish, played by Donald Crisp.
Duenna (as Tempe Pigett), played by Tempe Pigott.
Pirate Lieutenant, played by Sam De Grasse.
The Black Pirate is a 1926 American silent color adventure film directed by Albert Parker, starring
Douglas Fairbanks, Billie Dove, Donald Crisp, Sam De Grasse, and Anders Randolf.
After the first natural color films appeared in 1922,
Douglas Fairbanks envisioned a color pirate film.
However, he waited to start production until 1925.
Once Technicolor had improved its filming and printing capacity, Fairbanks took
financial risks due to the added costs and fragility of the film process.
He also hesitated because color was rumored to distract
from the narrative and strain viewers’ eyes.
To address these concerns, Fairbanks avoided Technicolor’s saturated tones and instead chose a restricted palette, inspired by
Flemish painters and American illustrators who had popularized pirate themes in the early twentieth century.
His team spent months testing and refining color control for all
on-screen elements, including the studio-created ocean.
This focus on visual consistency also led to the simplification
of the story, contributing to the film’s success.
Fairbanks continued to deliver his signature acrobatic stunts.
The film achieved international success, notably for its colors, but
suffered from the fragility of its two-strip laminated film.
This issue prompted Technicolor to abandon the process and develop a more
durable single-strip film, which was later used for some prints.
The Black Pirate became both a commercial and technical milestone, showcasing
Fairbanks’s influence, while also exposing the process’s limitations.
In his subsequent films, Fairbanks considered using Technicolor
again but gave up on it for various reasons.
In 1928, when Technicolor felt that it had overcome the difficulties encountered with The Black Pirate, it
produced The Viking (1928) as a demonstration, for which Fairbanks' film would serve as a hidden model.
Other successful films, including The Black Swan (1942) with Tyrone Power, and The Crimson Pirate (1952) with
Burt Lancaster would further exploit the link he had imagined between pirates and Technicolor.
The tone is emotional.